(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners, welcome
back to English Pod, my name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- Today we're bringing you an upper intermediate
lesson and something that we all do.
- Right, talking to ourselves.
- Talking to ourselves, right?
I think everyone does it, you think
to yourself or you talk to yourself.
- Yep.
- And we're gonna be doing that today,
but we're gonna be looking
at some specific vocabulary.
Erica, why don't you tell us about that?
- Well, unfortunately
we're gonna be following a
guy as he's in a really
embarrassing situation.
And we're gonna hear him call
himself some bad names in his mind.
- So he's a little bit nervous and
he thinks he is not very smart, right?
- That's right.
Okay, so before we start with this
dialogue, there are a couple of words
that we should look at
in vocabulary preview.
- Very vocabulary preview.
- All right, we're gonna
hear both of these words
in the dialogue and
the first one is famished.
- Famished.
- Okay, so famished is an adjective?
That's right, meaning
very, very, very hungry.
- Very, very hungry, okay.
So just very hungry, very easy.
- Yes, famished.
- Now what about our next one?
Sexist.
- Sexist.
- Another adjective to
describe a person, right?
- Right, or a thing, I
guess, like, yeah, an idea.
- Okay, so a sexist person would be
somebody who judges people by their sex.
So like all women are stupid, for example.
Which is not true, of course.
- No, of course not.
- Right, so sex is works both ways.
A woman can be sexist,
a man could be sexist.
- Exactly.
Meaning the women
thinks all men are stupid.
- Which is also not true.
- Yes, let's just be clear about that.
- All right, so now that we've taken a look
at these two phrases,
let's start with our dialogue
and we'll be back to talk
about all the great words.
(upbeat music)
- Me, your salad.
- Mm, looks good, impositively famished.
- And for you, sir, thank you.
Enjoy.
- Thank you.
- I can't believe she's on a date with me.
I'm so lucky.
I must be the luckiest guy in the world.
I wanna scream at the top of my lungs.
I'm luckiest dude in the world.
Oh, shut up.
Don't be such a dumbass.
She's so hot.
Wait, I can't say that.
Good, it's sexist.
She's so hot.
She's making me sexist.
Oh my God.
I'm such a tool.
Okay, get it together.
Oh, she's a doo salad.
All right, never salad.
Don't crap, which fork do I use?
Damn it.
She's gonna think I'm a moron.
What the hell are all these forks for?
Which one did she use?
Okay, chill.
Be cool, be cool.
Just take a fork, you need your salad.
Um, hmm?
Oh, sorry.
What were you saying?
You're eating my salad.
Oh, yes.
It's delicious.
Okay, embarrassing first date, huh?
Yeah, I mean, I really
do feel sorry for this guy.
Well, it happens to us.
Sometimes we are in
the company of a very
beautiful girl and we
just get really nervous.
All right, well, you know,
psychologists call this negative self-talk.
Really?
Yeah, this sort of calling yourself names
and talking negatively about yourself.
But actually, you can use some of this
language to talk negatively about others.
Yeah.
So why don't we look now at this
language in language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
So on language takeaway
today, we have five words.
Let's start with our first one.
Dumbass.
Okay, now this isn't a very polite word.
I would say.
Definitely not polite.
Okay, but what is a dumbass?
Well, it's obviously a dumb, stupid idiot.
Okay, so it's a person
that is not very intelligent.
And our next word is also quite similar.
Moron.
A moron.
If a person is a dumbass or a person
is a moron, what's the difference?
Well, basically, a moron is someone who
is not smart, who is very unintelligent.
Okay.
So they don't know what
OnePlus One is, all right?
But a dumbass is a person
who does stupid things.
Okay.
So maybe a dumbass,
like you're planning a bank
robbery and the dumbass
forgets to bring the gun.
Okay, that is a dumbass, okay.
So maybe more on is
a little bit less offensive
and it's actually, you'll find
it in the dictionary, right?
Yeah.
Whereas a dumbass, I
don't think you'll find it.
Yeah, it's slang.
It's slang, exactly.
Now, what about this next?
It's also a negative
name you can call people.
A tool, tool, tool.
This is very strange
because I don't know how a
tool can be something
negative towards a person.
Yeah.
But it actually means the opposite, right?
If a person is called a tool,
it means they are useless.
Right? Yeah.
So if you ever call the tool,
they're saying that you're useless.
Exactly.
You're good for nothing.
All right.
Well, these are three interesting words.
So why don't we hear some
examples of each of these words in use?
Example one, I hate
Tom, he's such a dumbass.
Last week he borrowed my mobile
phone and dropped it in the pool.
Example two, I don't like Kevin very much.
Maybe a real moron at times.
Example three.
It was looking for a job, but he
didn't even have a resume prepared.
He's such a tool.
Okay.
So great examples.
And here at EnglishPod, we're
bringing you real street talk.
Exactly.
Language as it is spoken by today's youth.
Okay.
Now let's take a look
at our last two words.
All right.
This is you can use
when you're trying to
calm yourself down and make
yourself relax a little bit, right?
Right.
Let's take a look at the next one.
Chill.
Okay.
So again, relax.
Calm down.
Yeah.
You need to chill.
Yes.
And then you also need to be cool.
Be cool.
Now, if you can tell the pattern
is related to temperature, right?
Yeah.
So is cold.
Cool is similar to cold.
Yeah.
It means to relax to calm down your
emotions, make your emotions not so hot.
Exactly.
Yeah.
All right.
So chill.
Be cool.
Exactly.
And you use them together like that.
Don't you?
Yeah.
Now, chill also has another
way of using it, right?
Exactly.
You can say, I'm chilling with my friends.
Yeah.
We're chilling here in
the EnglishPod studio.
Which means we're just relaxing.
Yeah.
You're just having fun.
Not doing anything, right?
Exactly.
But you can't say chilling.
You have to, you have to drop the G.
Yeah.
Yeah, you have to drop.
Right.
You can't say I'm chilling.
Yeah.
You have to say I'm chilling.
I'm chilling.
Okay.
So that's all for language takeaway.
But now let's take a
look at some of the really
useful phrases that we saw in
this dialogue in Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
Okay.
So this guy is so happy
he's on this date that
he wants to scream
at the top of his lungs.
Scream at the top of my lungs.
So basically he just wants to
like scream to show really loudly.
Really loudly.
Yeah.
He's so excited, right?
Exactly.
Okay.
So for example, sometimes
you're at a concert, right?
Yep.
And you need to
talk to your friend and
you're like screaming
at the top of your
lungs because the other
person can't hear you.
Exactly.
Or maybe you're lost in the woods
and you need to scream at the
top of your lungs so that
someone will hear you and find you.
All right.
Very good.
Okay.
So scream at the top of my lungs.
Our next phrase.
Get it together.
So if I tell you, Erica, you
need to get it together.
Basically you're telling
me to calm down, relax.
So pull your emotions together
and get your ideas straight.
Right.
So it kind of gives
you this idea that you
got to pull, like you
said, pull your emotions
together in a little
box and tie them up.
All right.
So get it together.
Yep.
So Marco, when would you use this phrase?
Get it together.
I guess when somebody
is either very emotional,
maybe crying or very
nervous, you know,
you tell the person, oh, get
it together, you know, relax.
Yeah.
Or when somebody maybe
is not doing something
good in their life,
you know, like making
bad decisions or not
being responsible, you
tell that person, you
need to get it together.
Exactly.
Right.
I couldn't have set up better myself.
Okay.
So now why don't we
move on to our next phrase
and this is really,
really high frequency.
I think you would hear it all the time.
All right.
So what the hell?
What the hell?
So why would you say what the hell?
Well, obviously you're
asking a question, right?
Right.
Because you got your,
your W, you got your what?
But when you say the hell, you're
putting emphasis on the what?
So you're asking a really strong question.
Right.
But it's not polite.
It's not polite.
Yep.
Okay.
So if I say what the
hell is going on, um,
what's happening really,
really what's happening.
Right.
Yeah.
So, and we can change it a little bit.
We can replace the what
with another WH, like why?
How?
Where?
Where or when?
Yeah.
Okay.
So why don't we hear
some examples of how this
expression is used using
different WH words?
Example one.
Where the hell are you?
I've been waiting for hours.
Level two.
How the hell did you do that?
That was amazing.
Example three.
When the hell are you going to find
a job, I'm tired of pay for everything.
Example four.
Who the hell are you?
I don't know you.
All right.
Now our final word, also a little bit
strong, um, but pretty high frequency.
Oh, yeah.
Very high frequency.
Oh, crap.
So it's a little bit
strong, but less strong
than maybe saying a
really bad word, right?
Yes.
But it's definitely saying, like,
you made a mistake, right?
Yeah.
It's like a really strong, oh, no.
Oh, no.
Exactly.
Yeah.
But I guess not many people say,
oh, no, oh, no, I just lost $10 million.
Exactly, right?
You would not say that.
Yeah.
So it's a very strong, oh, no, but
it's not as strong as it could be.
There are other words
out there that are
stronger, but we are not
going to go into them here.
But maybe you guys know, so let us know.
Yeah.
We can definitely keep a eye
out on the comments section.
But don't write the words
on the comments section.
Okay.
So we saw some really great
phrases, some really great words.
A lot of informal
language, but it's very
high frequency, and
you'll use that with your
friends or you'll see
it in movies, TV shows.
Yes.
Really common in movies and in TV shows.
Exactly.
So let's listen to this
dialogue one more time, and
then we'll come back
and talk a little bit more.
[MUSIC]
Miss, your salad looks
good and positively famished.
And for you, sir, thank you.
Enjoy, thank you.
[MUSIC]
I can't believe she's on the date with me.
I'm so lucky.
I must be the luckiest guy in the world.
I want to scream at the top of my lungs.
I'm lucky as to do it in the world.
Oh, shut up.
Don't be such a dumbass.
She's so hot.
Wait, I can't say that.
Good, it's sexist.
She's so hot.
She's making me sexist.
Oh my God, I'm such a tool.
Okay, get it to the other.
Oh, she's doing salad.
All right, never salad.
Don't crap, which fork do I use?
Damn it, she's gonna think I'm a moron.
What the hell are all these forks for?
We're trying to choose, okay, chill.
Be cool, be cool.
Just take a fork, you need your salad.
[MUSIC]
Mm, sorry, what were you saying?
You're eating my salad.
Oh, yes, it's delicious.
[MUSIC]
So these slang words, they're
actually very common, right?
Yeah, I think like you said, it's not likely
that you'll find them in a dictionary.
Of course, and you can find them in movies.
Or sometimes when
you're having a conversation
and very informal
conversation with a native
speaker, these words will slip out
and these slang terms will come up.
Exactly, and you know what?
There's a great resource
out there for wonderful
English slang terms
called urbandictionary.com.
Exactly, if you ever
see a word that maybe
you can find in the conventional dictionary,
you're probably gonna find it there.
Yeah, we'll put a link
up to it on the site.
All right, so also, if
you have any questions
or comments, be sure to
come to our website englishpod.
com, Marco and I are there to answer
all your questions, and we also got lots
of resources, like links
to urbandictionary.
Right, and also, if you have any questions
on any other slang terms that you may have
heard or how to use them, be sure
to post it on the comments section.
Well, guys, thanks for listening to
this lesson, and until next time, goodbye.
[MUSIC]